<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prd id="002" title="Writing index — typographic editorial redesign" project="uxward" created="2026-06-10" status="implemented">

  <overview>
    Covers Freya Work Order WO-003. A full redesign of the Writing index (/writing) from a
    collapsible accordion list into a typographic editorial index — a serious archive's table
    of contents. Each essay becomes one row: serif title (left), a dotted hairline leader, and
    the mono quarter (right). The three argued sections (On Leadership / On Experience Design /
    On AI) become always-open with big quiet § numerals; all accordion/collapse/section-focus
    machinery is removed. On hover or keyboard focus a row's title turns signature red and its
    deck reveals beneath (no layout shift). The search filter is simplified to a quiet
    type-to-filter (count + clear, per-section empty states).

    This PRD also carries one small site-wide change: the owner promoted red-on-hover to the
    standard link/title hover convention (visual-direction.md updated), so the home page's
    title hovers move from tertiary grey to signature red to match /writing.

    No backend work — static Astro site, one file rewritten (src/pages/writing/index.astro) plus
    a surgical hover-colour edit on src/pages/index.astro. The essays data file (src/data/essays.js)
    and the masthead voice are explicitly out of scope and must not change. The featured-essay
    pull on /writing is left exactly as built (owner directive).
  </overview>

  <scope>
    <scenarios>03-pierce-the-peer (primary), 01-vivian-the-vp + 02-tessa-the-talent-partner (pass-through)</scenarios>
    <views>Writing index (/writing) — full redesign; Home (/) — hover-colour only</views>
    <platform>None. Static site. Reads existing src/data/essays.js; no data, API, or DB work.</platform>
  </scope>

  <requirements>

    <requirement id="002-REQ-001" type="interface" status="implemented">
      <title>Editorial index structure — leader-dots rows + always-open sections</title>
      <description>
        Rewrite the body of src/pages/writing/index.astro so each essay renders as a single
        table-of-contents row: an &lt;a&gt; to /writing/&lt;slug&gt; containing the serif title
        (rendered with set:html to preserve the &lt;em&gt; clause, --ink at rest), a flexible
        dotted hairline leader in --rule (decorative, aria-hidden/pure-CSS, never real text),
        and the mono quarter right-aligned (--tertiary, e.g. "Q4 2014"). Render the three
        sections from essaySections + essays (already grouped, newest-first within each) as
        ALWAYS-OPEN: each with a big quiet § numeral in the gutter (§ 01/02/03), the &lt;h2&gt;
        title, the existing descriptor, and a --rule hairline. Remove the &lt;button class="section-toggle"&gt;,
        aria-expanded, the toggle glyph, and the .collapsed / .section-collapsed-msg /
        "Hidden. Click to expand." machinery entirely. Per-row deck text is rendered but hidden
        at rest (revealed in REQ-002); mirror plain title + deck onto data-title / data-deck via
        plainTitle() for the filter. Keep the masthead (eyebrow, H1, intro) and the /about pivot;
        keep the featured pull EXACTLY as built.
      </description>
      <acceptance>
        <criterion>Each of the 23 essays renders as one row: serif title (left) · dotted --rule leader · mono quarter (right).</criterion>
        <criterion>The dotted leader is decorative only — not selectable text, not exposed to assistive tech, not matched by the filter.</criterion>
        <criterion>Three always-open sections render with § 01/02/03 gutter numerals, their titles, and descriptors: On Leadership (10), On Experience Design (11), On AI (2).</criterion>
        <criterion>No toggle &lt;button&gt;, aria-expanded attribute, toggle glyph, or .collapsed/"Hidden, click to expand" element exists anywhere in the rendered DOM.</criterion>
        <criterion>The featured-essay pull markup is byte-for-byte the same as before this PRD (3px --signature left border, red eyebrow, deck, excerpt, CTA). [Its hide-on-filter behavior was later removed per REQ-007 — markup/visual unchanged.]</criterion>
        <criterion>The H1 "Writing, arranged by what it argues." and the intro ending "Quarterly. Long-form. No newsletter to sign up for." are present verbatim.</criterion>
        <criterion>npm run build passes; counts derive from essays.js (eyebrow shows the real total).</criterion>
      </acceptance>
      <refs>
        <spec>D-UX-Design/writing-index.md</spec>
        <wireframe>D-UX-Design/wireframes/writing-index.png</wireframe>
      </refs>
    </requirement>

    <requirement id="002-REQ-002" type="interface" status="implemented">
      <title>Row hover/focus — red title + deck reveal (no reflow)</title>
      <description>
        On hover AND :focus-visible of a row, shift the title colour --ink → --signature (colour
        only — no weight/style/position change, no WONK lean) and reveal the essay's deck (quiet
        serif italic) beneath the title. Use a 150ms (--t-fast) colour transition. Prevent layout
        shift by reserving the deck's vertical space at rest (deck rendered, opacity:0, fading to
        1 on hover/focus). Under prefers-reduced-motion: reduce, swap opacity instantly (no fade).
        Keyboard parity is mandatory: focus produces the identical red+deck state plus the standard
        2px --signature focus ring. The /about pivot hover also moves to --signature (was tertiary).
      </description>
      <acceptance>
        <criterion>Hovering a row turns its title --signature red (colour only) and shows its deck; both revert on mouse-out.</criterion>
        <criterion>Hovering a mid-list row causes NO vertical movement of the rows below it (space reserved).</criterion>
        <criterion>Tabbing to a row by keyboard shows the identical red-title + deck-revealed state plus a 2px --signature focus ring; every row is reachable in DOM order.</criterion>
        <criterion>With prefers-reduced-motion: reduce, the colour/deck change is instant (no fade); no movement.</criterion>
        <criterion>The /about pivot link hovers to --signature red, not tertiary.</criterion>
        <criterion>Hover red works correctly in both light and dark mode.</criterion>
      </acceptance>
      <refs>
        <spec>D-UX-Design/writing-index.md</spec>
        <wireframe>D-UX-Design/wireframes/writing-index.png</wireframe>
      </refs>
    </requirement>

    <requirement id="002-REQ-003" type="interface" status="implemented">
      <title>Simplified filter — count + clear, per-section empty states</title>
      <description>
        Keep a quiet type-to-filter; strip the section-focus machinery. Match the trimmed,
        lowercased query against each row's data-title + data-deck; set hidden on non-matching
        rows; empty query shows all rows. The result line (aria-live="polite") shows count + clear
        ONLY — e.g. "— 4 essays · Clear —" — with no "X shown", no "Section:" fragment, no
        multi-part status string. When a section has zero matches under the query, show a quiet
        italic "— No matches in {section title}. —" in place of its rows while still rendering its
        head + § numeral. [SUPERSEDED by REQ-007: the featured pull now stays visible while
        filtering — the body.is-filtered hide behavior was removed.] Remove state.activeSection, the
        .collapsed toggling, the .section-toggle click handlers, and the "Clear all" multi-part hint.
      </description>
      <acceptance>
        <criterion>Typing filters rows live: non-matching rows are hidden; clearing restores all rows, the featured pull, and focus to the input.</criterion>
        <criterion>The result line shows only a count + clear control (e.g. "— 4 essays · Clear —"); no "Section:" or "X shown" text appears.</criterion>
        <criterion>A query matching nothing in one section shows "— No matches in {title}. —" under that section's still-visible head; other sections show their matches.</criterion>
        <criterion>A query matching nothing site-wide shows the empty message in all three sections and "— 0 essays · Clear —".</criterion>
        <criterion>No section-focus, collapse, or activeSection code path remains in the page script.</criterion>
      </acceptance>
      <refs>
        <spec>D-UX-Design/writing-index.md</spec>
        <wireframe>D-UX-Design/wireframes/writing-index.png</wireframe>
      </refs>
    </requirement>

    <requirement id="002-REQ-004" type="interface" status="implemented">
      <title>Responsive ≤880px — rows stack, leader dots drop</title>
      <description>
        At ≤880px: collapse the --gutter-mark column and move § numerals inline above each section
        title; stack rows so the title takes full width and the quarter moves below the title
        (mono, left-aligned); drop the dotted leader (or render a single short hairline) since the
        quarter is no longer right-aligned on the same baseline; make the filter input full-width
        and left-align the result line.
      </description>
      <acceptance>
        <criterion>At 375px wide there is no horizontal scroll and no overlap; rows are stacked with the quarter beneath the title.</criterion>
        <criterion>The leader dots are not rendered as a spanning element on stacked phone rows.</criterion>
        <criterion>§ numerals remain visible (inline) and the filter input is full-width.</criterion>
        <criterion>Hover/focus reveal (REQ-002) still works where a pointer/keyboard is available at small widths.</criterion>
      </acceptance>
      <refs>
        <spec>D-UX-Design/writing-index.md</spec>
        <wireframe>D-UX-Design/wireframes/writing-index.png</wireframe>
      </refs>
    </requirement>

    <requirement id="002-REQ-005" type="interface" status="implemented">
      <title>Site-wide hover convention — home page titles hover red</title>
      <description>
        Apply the new site-wide interaction-red convention to src/pages/index.astro: the home
        page's title hovers currently go to --tertiary; change them to --signature so the home
        page matches /writing. Specifically the case-card title hover (.case:hover .title) and the
        recent-essay title hover (.essay:hover .title), plus any other link/title hover currently
        resolving to --tertiary. Surgical — hover COLOUR only. Do not touch the fold, the §06
        red-bleed block, layout, or copy.
      </description>
      <acceptance>
        <criterion>On the home page, hovering a case-card title and a recent-essay title turns the title --signature red (not tertiary).</criterion>
        <criterion>No other home-page change: fold, red-bleed, layout, and copy are untouched (diff is hover-colour declarations only).</criterion>
        <criterion>Home page still builds and renders identically except for hover colour; works in light and dark mode.</criterion>
      </acceptance>
      <refs>
        <spec>A-Product-Brief/visual-direction.md (red registers); E-Development/WO-003-writing-index.md §B</spec>
        <wireframe></wireframe>
      </refs>
    </requirement>

    <requirement id="002-REQ-006" type="interface" status="implemented">
      <title>View toggle — Topic / Date arrangement + controls band</title>
      <description>
        Add a Topic/Date view toggle and relocate the controls. (1) Move the filter OUT of the
        masthead into a new controls band that sits between the featured pull and the list; the
        band holds the view toggle (left) and the filter (right), with the result line beneath.
        (2) The toggle is quiet mono — "— Arrange — Topic | Date" — two buttons with aria-pressed,
        active state ink + underline, NO red (administrative chrome; inactive grey). (3) Render BOTH
        arrangements server-side: #view-topic (the existing three § sections) and #view-date (one
        flat list from essaysNewestFirst, no sections, each row carrying a topic tag in its meta
        cluster as "TOPIC · QUARTER", tag derived from essaySections minus the "On " prefix). The
        toggle swaps which view is visible via a data-view attribute. (4) The choice is persisted in
        localStorage (key uxward:writing-view) and restored on load; default Topic. (5) The filter
        operates on the visible view: per-section empty messages in Topic, a single "— No matches. —"
        in Date; an active query persists across a toggle. The H1 stays static in both modes. The
        featured pull shows in both modes and still hides while filtering. View swap is instant (no
        animation). essays.js is not modified.
      </description>
      <acceptance>
        <criterion>The filter no longer sits in the masthead; it and the view toggle live in a controls band between the featured pull and the first row, toggle left / filter right.</criterion>
        <criterion>Toggle shows two options Topic|Date in mono; the active one is ink + underline, the inactive grey; neither is red; both are keyboard-operable with aria-pressed reflecting state.</criterion>
        <criterion>Topic view renders the three § sections (unchanged). Date view renders one flat list, newest→oldest, with NO § sections and each row showing "TOPIC · QUARTER" (e.g. "EXPERIENCE DESIGN · Q2 2021").</criterion>
        <criterion>Clicking Date then reloading the page returns to Date (persisted in localStorage); clearing storage / first visit shows Topic.</criterion>
        <criterion>Filtering works in whichever view is active: Topic shows per-section empty messages, Date shows a single "— No matches. —"; the count+clear line is identical; featured hides while filtering in both.</criterion>
        <criterion>The H1 "Writing, arranged by what it argues." is unchanged in both modes; hover/focus red+deck-reveal works on rows in both views; the topic tag does not turn red on hover.</criterion>
        <criterion>npm run build passes; src/data/essays.js is unmodified; the featured pull markup is still byte-identical.</criterion>
      </acceptance>
      <refs>
        <spec>D-UX-Design/writing-index.md</spec>
        <wireframe>D-UX-Design/wireframes/writing-index.png</wireframe>
      </refs>
    </requirement>

    <requirement id="002-REQ-007" type="interface" status="implemented">
      <title>Step-7 review refinements — featured always-visible, filter chrome, filter/view motion</title>
      <description>
        Owner refinements during the step-7 design review (2026-06-10). (1) FEATURED ALWAYS VISIBLE:
        the featured pull no longer hides while filtering — supersedes the hide-on-filter behavior
        specified in REQ-003 (the body.is-filtered rule and class toggle are removed). (2) FILTER
        CHROME: the result line is count-only ("— N essays —") — the inline "Clear" link is removed;
        the in-field × is the sole clear affordance. The placeholder is "Filter essays" (no
        surrounding dashes) at 50% opacity, fading to 0 on focus and back to 50% on blur (150ms).
        (3) FILTER MOTION: filtered rows fade out (150ms opacity) then collapse height/padding
        (150ms, delayed) so remaining rows reflow up — implemented via a .filtered-out class with
        staggered transitions (no display:none toggle); collapsed rows leave the a11y/tab order
        (visibility hidden, delayed past the motion). (4) VIEW MOTION: the Topic↔Date swap is a
        ~120ms cross-fade dip (fade out active view, swap, fade in). (5) Both motions are instant
        under prefers-reduced-motion. Also folded in earlier in the review: row-to-row dividers
        removed; leader dots switched to a radial-gradient with a wide 8px gap.
      </description>
      <acceptance>
        <criterion>Featured pull stays visible while filtering in both Topic and Date views.</criterion>
        <criterion>Result line shows count only ("— N essays —"); no inline Clear link/button exists; the in-field × clears the input and restores all rows.</criterion>
        <criterion>Placeholder is "Filter essays" (no dashes), 50% opacity at rest, fades to 0 on focus and back to 50% on blur.</criterion>
        <criterion>A filtered-out row ends at opacity 0, max-height 0, visibility hidden (faded then collapsed); a kept row stays opaque; clearing restores all 23.</criterion>
        <criterion>Topic↔Date toggle cross-fades (no hard cut); after settle the data-view is swapped, vw-leaving/vw-entering classes are cleaned up, and the shown view is fully opaque.</criterion>
        <criterion>Under prefers-reduced-motion: reduce, both the filter and the view swap apply instantly (verified at ~80ms).</criterion>
        <criterion>npm run build passes; essays.js unmodified; featured markup still byte-identical.</criterion>
      </acceptance>
      <refs>
        <spec>D-UX-Design/writing-index.md</spec>
        <wireframe>D-UX-Design/wireframes/writing-index.png</wireframe>
      </refs>
    </requirement>

  </requirements>

  <test-protocol>
    <!-- Verified 2026-06-10 via Playwright/Chromium against `npm run preview` (localhost:4322).
         26 automated assertions, all PASS — desktop 1440px, mobile 375px, light + dark, keyboard. -->
    <test ref="002-REQ-001">
      <steps>Load /writing. Count a.essay rows; count .section; read .essay-lead border-style + aria-hidden; grep DOM for section-toggle/aria-expanded/glyph on the sections; confirm featured markup + masthead lines present.</steps>
      <expected>23 rows; 3 sections; leader border-bottom-style=dotted, aria-hidden=true; 0 accordion elements on sections (the aria-expanded/glyph in DOM belong to the site header, identical on /); featured pull + "arranged by what it argues" + "No newsletter to sign up for" present. PASS.</expected>
    </test>
    <test ref="002-REQ-002">
      <steps>Read first deck opacity at rest. Hover row 1: read title color + deck opacity; compare document.scrollHeight before/after. Tab to first a.essay; after settle, read :focus-visible, title color, deck opacity, outline color. Repeat hover in dark mode (data-theme=dark).</steps>
      <expected>Rest deck opacity=0. Hover: title rgb(204,0,6), deck opacity=1, scrollHeight 5164→5164 (no reflow). Keyboard focus: matches :focus-visible, title rgb(204,0,6), deck opacity=1, outline rgb(204,0,6). Dark: canvas rgb(18,18,18), hover title rgb(229,38,58), deck revealed. PASS.</expected>
    </test>
    <test ref="002-REQ-003">
      <steps>Type "buffalo" → count visible rows, read #search-hint, read #featured display, check On AI section .no-matches + empty msg. Type "zzzqqq" → count visible + hint. Click #search-clear → count visible + featured display.</steps>
      <expected>"buffalo": 1 visible, hint "— 1 essay · Clear —" (no Section/shown), featured display:none, On AI shows empty message. "zzzqqq": 0 visible, hint "— 0 essays · Clear —". Clear: 23 visible, featured display:block. PASS.</expected>
    </test>
    <test ref="002-REQ-004">
      <steps>At 375px load /writing. Read .essay-lead display; compare quarter.top vs title.bottom within a row; check document.scrollingElement.scrollWidth ≤ innerWidth.</steps>
      <expected>Leader display:none; quarter sits below title; no horizontal overflow at 375px. PASS.</expected>
    </test>
    <test ref="002-REQ-005">
      <steps>Load /. Hover .case .title and .essay .title; read computed color.</steps>
      <expected>Both hover to rgb(204,0,6) signature (light); resolves to the dark signature in dark mode via the token. PASS. (Global a:hover remains tertiary by design — only title hovers were promoted, per PRD scope.)</expected>
    </test>
    <test ref="002-REQ-006">
      <steps>Load /writing. Check controls band order (featured→controls→list), filter out of head. Read toggle default (Topic active+ink+underline, aria-pressed; no red). Click Date: assert topic hidden / date shown, 0 sections, 23 flat rows, first meta "TOPIC · QUARTER" newest-first. Reload → expect Date (localStorage). Filter per view; hover a Date row.</steps>
      <expected>Controls between featured and list; filter in controls not head. Topic default active, Date grey, neither red. Date = 23 flat rows, "Experience Design · Q1 2026" first. Persists across reload. Filter scoped to active view (Topic per-section empty, Date single empty). Date hover → title red + deck, tag stays grey. H1 unchanged. 18/18 PASS.</expected>
    </test>
    <test ref="002-REQ-007">
      <steps>Filter "buffalo" (settle 450ms): count visible by !.filtered-out, read result line + featured display, read a filtered-out row's opacity/max-height/visibility. Clear via × → recount. Toggle Date (settle): read data-view, vw-* leftover classes, #view-date opacity. Placeholder: read ::placeholder opacity at rest / focus / blur. Reduced-motion context: filter + toggle, check at 80ms.</steps>
      <expected>1 visible; "— 1 essay —" (no Clear button); featured display:block. filtered-out row opacity 0 / max-height 0px / visibility hidden; kept row opacity 1; clear restores 23. After toggle: data-view=date, no vw-leaving/vw-entering, #view-date opacity 1, topic display:none. Placeholder 0.5 → 0 (focus) → 0.5 (blur). Reduced-motion: 1 visible and view=date already at 80ms. 21/21 PASS (consolidated final suite).</expected>
    </test>
  </test-protocol>

</prd>
